So because the loads in our processor
need to be done as soon as possible
while the stores do not write to memory
until commit. We said we need a loadster
Q so that we can supply the values from
stores to loads.
This loster Q or LSQ is a structure just
like the ROB meaning we put things there
in order and remove them at commit but
we only put load and store instructions
there. So there is a bit that says which
instruction do we have load or store.
There is a field for what is the address
this instruction is accessing and there
is a field for the value that the
instruction should be storing or
loading. There is also a field for this
instruction has been completed. Now
let's suppose we have this program and
suppose that the loq is initially empty.
So as we said things are going to be
placed here in program order. So the
first instruction here is going to be a
load. Let's say that we quickly compute
the address and it's
104. This load because there are no
previous stores will go to memory. The
next instruction here is a store. Let's
say that it computes the address of 204.
Let's say that the value is 15 and we
mark it done. And let's say that this
instruction is kind of delayed, so it
doesn't return yet. So we still have all
of these in the loster Q. The next load
let's say it eventually computes the
address of 204. For every load when it
computes the address, we check in the
load store if any store matches that
address. If there is no matching store
like equals case for this load because
there were no stores, we go to memory.
If there is a matching store, we do not
go to memory. Instead we do what is
called the store to load forwarding
where we simply take the value from the
store and that is the value that the
load produces and we never go to memory.
So again this is called store to load
forwarding. Now, of course, this assumes
that at the time we want to do this
load, the stores have already been
completed and we now know what the
addresses are and if we need to get the
value, we know what the value This